Guide to the Howard "Stretch" Johnson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Howard "Stretch" Johnson Papers,
1923-2011
[Bulk Dates: 1980-2000].
Johnson, Howard E.
5 linear ft. (6 document boxes, 2 flat boxes, 1 index card box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1634
9681555
The Howard "Stretch" Johnson Papers document the life of Howard Johnson, known for most of his life as "Stretch." Johnson was a tap dancer with the Duke Ellington Orchestra and performed in Harlem at the Cotton Club and the Apollo Theater in the 1930s. After joining the Communist Party of the United States of America in 1940, Johnson went on to engage in social activism for most of his life, living in a number of places, including Brazil, Galveston, Texas, Hawaii, Paris, and St. Croix. The Papers contain correspondence, both personal and work related, as well as a nearly finished typescript of Stretch's autobiography. There are a number of photographs, mainly copies of the various performers at the Cotton Club, as well as audio and videocassettes, and ephemera. Additionally, the collection contains a family scrapbook with photos from the late 1940s and early 1950s.
Biographical Note
Howard "Stretch" Johnson was born in 1915 in Orange, New Jersey. He lived a colorful life, tap dancing with the Duke Ellington Orchestra at the Cotton Club and the Apollo in Harlem, serving in World War II in the army's segregated Buffalo Soldier unit, joining the Communist Party USA in 1940, and finally teaching about the history of jazz and engaging in social activism. Johnson was given the nickname "Stretch" for his long and lanky frame, which he maintained throughout most of his life.
Johnson's father gained stardom by playing on the black baseball teams of the Negro League. Stretch, however, more closely identified with his uncle, James Anderson, who was the founder of The Amsterdam News, an influential black newspaper in New York City. The Johnson family moved to Harlem in 1932, where Stretch's sister, Winnie became one of the featured dancers at the Cotton Club. She enlisted Stretch and later their brother Bobby to join the chorus line. The Johnson siblings performing under the name The Three Johnsons were featured in the ''New Faces of 1936'' and the ''Duke Ellington Revue of 1937'' at the Apollo Theater. Stretch Johnson also acted in a Harlem production of the Clifford Odets play, Waiting for Lefty.
Johnson was active with the NAACP since he was 15 years old. In 1940, when the Cotton Club decided to suspend its male chorus line, Johnson joined the Young Communist League of Harlem, a youth affiliate of the Communist Party of the United States of America. He was active in forcing Major League Baseball to accept a black player, passing out petitions at Yankee Stadium.
Amidst objection, Johnson married Martha Sherman, a fellow communist. The couple had three children, all girls. Sherman and Johnson eventually divorced. Johnson earned a general equivalency high school diploma, then a degree from Columbia University's College of General Studies, and taught black studies at the Fieldston School in the Bronx. He administered the Upward Bound program, which provided federal money for programs to steer disadvantaged youths to college for a participating institution, the Ethical Culture Society. He later taught sociology at the State University of New York at New Paltz.
Stretch spent his later years with Ann Anthony, whom he met at an Art Appreciation course at Columbia University in 1962. The two lived in numerous places, engaging in activist causes wherever they went. This included a campaign to recognize Martin Luther King Jr. Day in Hawaii, in the Virgin Islands he set up a social services network, and in Galveston, Texas, he helped set up a community center in an impoverished neighborhood.
Scope and Content
This small collection contains the personal papers of Howard "Stretch" Johnson. The materials range in date from 1923-2000 and consist of correspondence, clippings, and printed material as well as photographs, negatives, slides, audio and videocassettes, a scrapbook, and ephemeral material. Included are Johnson's notes and typescript for his nearly finished autobiography, as well as numerous letters, both personal and work-related. A number of folders are present which present Johnson as "Social and Political Figure." These folders contain material which relates to work that Johnson did with the Communist Party USA and also later as a social activist in Brazil, Galveston, Texas, Hawaii, Paris, and St. Croix. A transcript is present of Johnson testifying under the Smith Act trials as a witness for the defense. There is material related to work that "Stretch" did as a professor at the State University of New York at New Paltz, under the folder title, "The Educator." Several of Johnson's writings are present, including a pamphlet he wrote for the National Veterans Committee of the Communist Party USA under the folder title, "Author." There are a number of photographs in the collection, mainly copies, of performers at the Cotton Club as well as articles and clippings about the Cotton Club, and jazz more generally. The collection contains several audio and videocassettes, of note are various interviews with Johnson. The scrapbook is made up of family photographs, mainly of "Stretch", his wife, and their children ranging in date from 1945-1952.
Arrangement
Material is arranged into one series
Series I: Howard "Stretch" Johnson Papers.
Subjects
Apollo Theatre (New York, N.Y.: 42nd Street).; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Cotton Club.; Duke Ellington Orchestra.; Johnson, Howard E.; Tap dancing.; Harlem Renaissance.; Audiocassettes.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Videocassettes.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least 2 business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Wendy Johnson Purchase 09/14/2012 2012.2013.M044
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Howard "Stretch" Johnson Papers, 1923-2011
  - Documents, Photographs, and Negatives
    - Political and Social Figure
      - New Paltz, New York, 1947-1963, 1971-1982, undated (Box 1)
      - Brazil, 1988 (Box 1)
      - St. Croix, 1991 (Box 1)
      - Paris, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
      - Galveston, Texas, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
      - Obituaries, 2000 (Box 1)
      - Dr. Martin Luther King Interim Commission Report, 1990 (Box 1)
      - Hawaii, 1986-1990, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - Smith Act Trail--Transcript of Johnson's Testimony, Witness for the Defense, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Jackie Robinson Project, 1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Cotton Club Venue
      - Copies, 1928-1933, 1980, undated (Box 1)
      - Photographs of Frequenters, 1923-1932, undated (Box 2)
      - Related Articles, 1928-1977, 1984, undated (Box 2)
      - Photographs of Performers, Bands, and Show Details, 1933-1937, undated (Box 2)
    - Cotton Club Film
      - Articles and Related Writings, 1980-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Stretch and the Government--the Ongoing Battle, 1981-1995, undated (Box 2)
    - Literature on Harlem and Jazz, 1930, 1988-1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Health, 1999, undated (Box 2)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 2)
    - Slides, undated (Box 2)
    - Copies of Photographs, 1934-1947, undated (Box 2)
    - Telegram, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Interview "Stretch's Life" Kay Takora, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Interview "Stretch's Life" Kay Takora, Honolulu, Hawaii--CDs, 1988 (Box 3)
    - "The Performer", 1936, 1942, 1983, undated (Box 3)
    - Interview and Letters on Stretch, 2011, undated (Box 3)
    - Term Papers, NYU, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Notes for Autobiography, undated (Box 3)
    - "Stretch" Autobiography, undated (Box 3)
    - Bibliography and Chronological Autobiography, undated (Box 3)
    - "Author", 1947-1995 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1946-2001 (Box 3)
    - Private Correspondence (Non-Work Related) and Personal Papers, 1957-1997, undated (Box 3)
    - "The Educator", 1974-1999, undated (Box 4)
    - Further Research, 1982-1995, undated (Box 4)
    - Handwritten, 1975-1978, undated (Box 4)
    - Letters, 1982-1995, undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-2000, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Books
    - Melanin: The Chemical Key to Black Greatness, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Natal Horoscope of Dr. Howard Johnson, undated (Box 5)
    - Report to the Governor of the State of Hawaii, Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Interim Commission, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Videocassettes
    - Blues Land: A Portrait in American Music, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Career Awareness Program Interview Howard Johnson on Harlem Renaissance, undated (Box 5)
    - Imitation of Life, 1959 (Box 5)
    - London Lindy Hop Festival Cabaret's Jiving Lindy Hoppers on TV, 1996, 1998 (Box 5)
    - Paul Robeson: Here I Stand, 1999; Paul Robeson Jr. and Ossie Davis, 1999; A Hymn for Alvin Ailey, 1999; Flying High: The Nicholas Brothers, 1999 (Box 5)
    - A Walk through Harlem, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Heir to an Execution (the Rosenbergs), Ivy Meeropol, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Paul Robeson, undated (Box 9)
    - Seeing Red, James Klein and Julia Reichert, undated (Box 9)
  - DVDs
    - Seeing Red, James Klein and Julia Reichert, undated (3 DVDs) (Box 9)
  - CDs
    - Felix Mendelssohn Violin Concerto in E Minor, 1998 (Box 5)
    - Johannes Brahms Sonata no. 1 for cello and piano Sonata no. 2; Yo-Yo Ma and Emmanual Ax, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Play On, Broadway Musical, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Audiocassettes
    - Discussion of Operation Desert Storm, 1991 (Box 6)
    - George, Dr. Herman--Race Relations, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Jamal, Mumia Abu--Speech at Press Conference at Unesco, Paris, France, 1995 (2 tapes) (Box 6)
    - Jamal, Mumia Abu Evening Centre Cult de la Clef, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Johnson, Howard--Interview, 1984 (4 tapes) (Box 6)
    - Johnson, Howard--Interview, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Mood Indigo Ellington Suites, undated (Box 6)
    - People of Color I and II Presentation by Howard Johnson, 1995 (2 tapes) (Box 6)
    - Radzin, Stenka--Cradle Will Rock, undated (Box 6)
    - Rehm, Diane--Seeing Red, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Scott-Heron, Gil and Jackson, Brian--Winter in America, undated (Box 6)
    - Thakar, Vimala--Mediation as a Way of Life, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks and Other Photographs
    - Souvenir Photographs, undated (2 photos) (Box 7)
    - Photographs, 1995-1999 undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook, 1944-1952 undated, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - Ephemera
    - Reproduction of $20 Gold Piece (Box 8)
    - Brazilian Workers Banner (Box 8)
    - Soviet Union Banner with 22 Pins from Trip to Moscow (Box 8)
    - Business Cards, Paris, France Address (5 items) (Box 8)
    - Silver AA Medallion with Chain (Box 8)
    - Green and Black Buffalo Soldier Pin (Box 8)
    - Soviet Union Pin, CCCP (Box 8)
    - Lacquered Russian Boxes (2 boxes) (Box 8)
    - USA Olympic Pin (Box 8)
    - Unidentified Pin (Box 8)
    - Subway Tokens (5 tokens) (Box 8)
    - Blanket in African-American Colors (Box 8)